Amina El-Ashry, Design Researcher

aminaelashry2@gmail.com | (571) 604-0314 | Austin, Texas, USA

/linkedin.com/in/amina-el-ashry

User Experience Researcher with **5+ years** in enterprise. Demonstrated history in early product discovery, strategy, and launch. Experienced in identifying product opportunities and gaps, assessing markets, communicating complex concepts, and synthesizing large amounts of data. Proven track record of fast, high-impact work in ambiguous environments.

EDUCATION

__

University of Maryland Baltimore County- M.S. Human-Centered Computing | B.S. Information Systems

EXPERIENCE

--

IBM, Design Researcher – Washington, DC

June 2021 - Present

- Led discovery research and market analysis for IBM Cloud's migration platform, driving redesign of user flows and solution packages improving customer retention by 40%
- Rapidly evaluated 15+ prototypes for IBM Concert through a series of concept testing studies, directly enabling MVP launch within 6 months and influencing development through weekly exec insights
- Identified investment gaps in IBM Software/IBM Research portfolio management practices, supporting org-wide
 product management transformation and building an internal tool used by 200+ leaders
- Supported 5 early-stage IBM ventures with discovery research and product-market fit workshops; 3 became viable products, attracting \$20M in funding
- Defined trial-to-purchase journey for IBM's Multi-Cloud SaaS Platform through generative research and workflow definition, resulting in 3000+ trial users and 40% conversion rate
- Launched survey to 260 IBM employees evaluating their current and future use of LLMs, informing 10 critical AI use
 cases across 5 roles

IBM, Design Research Intern (co-op) – Washington, DC

Jan. 2021 – May 2021

- Led discovery and generative research to define 3rd party integration strategy for IBM Red Hat Marketplace, introducing 2 core product capabilities and new user personas
- Uncovered key ML model generation workflow gaps, shaping core user flow for IBM's hybrid cloud platform concept
- Influenced IT spend dashboard design through quantitative survey and data analysis, benefitting 1000+ technical
 and executive IBM Red Hat Marketplace users
- Developed automation workflows for recruitment and insights tracking using Airtable

University of Maryland Baltimore County, HCI Researcher – Baltimore, MD

Oct. 2020 – Dec. 2024

- Led, designed, and conducted 3 international research studies on Human-Computer Interaction (HCI) practices in the Middle East, publishing in ACM CSCW and informing global understanding of HCI adoption
- Built relationships with regional academic and industry leaders to leverage local expertise and ensure research impact

Previous roles: Google (2020), Sofiac Travel (2019-2020), Cisco (2019)

SKILLS

--

Methods: Qualitative Research | Interviews | Surveys | Concept Testing | Competitive Analysis | Product-Market Fit | Value Proposition Testing | Usability Testing | Evaluative Research | Quantitative Research | Benchmarking | In-Person Research | Workshop Facilitation | Journey Maps | Participatory Design | Agile Development | Human-Centered Al Analysis: Qualitative Analysis | Thematic Analysis | Data Viz. | Descriptive Statistics | Python | SQL | C++ | HTML Leadership: Storytelling | Public Speaking | Critical Thinking | Executive Collaboration

Tools: Qualtrics | Figma | Mural | Airtable | Respondent.io | User Interviews | UserZoom | Dovetail | Overleaf

SELECTED AWARDS AND PUBLICATIONS

__

Awards: IBM Tech Award (2024) | IBM Growth Award (2024) | IBM Entrepreneur Award (2023) | IBM Eminence & Excellence Award (2022)

Publications: How Knowledge Workers Use and Want to Use LLMs in an Enterprise Context (IBM) | Exploring the Collaboration Possibilities of Distributed Making for Storytelling Using 3D Printing Pens (UMBC)

Please visit LinkedIn and Portfolio for more detail.